<cesDoc id="eng-w-social-sick" lang="eng">
<cesHeader type="text">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<h.title>eng-w-social-sick.txt</h.title>
<respStmt> 
<respType>Electronic file created by</respType>
<respName>Dept of Linguistics, Lancaster University</respName>
<respType>transcribed by</respType>
<respName>Paul Baker</respName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<distributor>UCREL</distributor>
<pubAddress>Dept of Linguistics, Lancaster University, Lancaster, LA1 4YT, UK</pubAddress>
<availability region="WORLD"></availability>
<pubDate>02-01-31</pubDate>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<h.title>Sick or disabled SD1</h.title>
<h.author>Department of Social Security</h.author>
<imprint>
<pubPlace>Leeds, UK</pubPlace>
<publisher>Department of Social Security</publisher>
<pubDate>October 2000</pubDate>
</imprint>
</monogr>
</biblStruct>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>Text collected for use in the EMILLE project, May 2000.</projectDesc>
<samplingDesc>Simple written text only has been transcribed. Diagrams, pictures and tables have been omitted and their place marked with a gap element.
</samplingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<conformance level="1"></conformance>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date>02-31-01</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>English</langUsage>
<wsdUsage>
<writingSystem id="ISO/IEC 10646">Universal Multiple-Octet Coded Character Set (UCS).</writingSystem>
</wsdUsage>
<textClass>
<channel mode="w">print</channel>
<constitution type="single"></constitution>
<derivation type="original"></derivation>
<domain type="public"></domain>
<factuality type="fact "></factuality>
</textClass>
<translations>
<translation trans.loc="NULL" lang="ENG" wsd="ISO8859-1" n="1"></translation>
</translations>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
</revisionDesc>
</cesHeader>

<text>
<body>
<p><head><s>Sick or disabled</s></head></p>

<p><s>A basic guide to benefits and tax credits for people of all ages with a physical or mental illness or disability - and for people who look after them</s></p>

<p><head><s>Sick or disabled</s></head></p>

<p><s>Sickness, injury and disability can come into someone's life at any time, often when least expected.</s> <s>You may be off work for some time because of sickness.</s> <s>Or you may be unable to work because of a serious illness or disability.</s></p>

<p><s>This leaflet is also for you if you look after someone who has an illness or disability that makes life difficult.</s></p>

<p><s>Whether you are the person who is sick or disabled, or you are looking after someone, you may be able to get social security benefits or tax credits to give you and your family financial help.</s></p>

<p><s>This leaflet gives basic advice on the benefits and tax credits you may be able to get.</s> <s>We want to make sure you and your family get the right help, at the right time, in the right way.</s></p>

<p><s>If you have a question which is not answered in the leaflet, or if you just want more advice, please contact your social security office.</s> <s>See Where to get help and advice on page 19 of this leaflet for details.</s></p>

<p><s>Remember that this leaflet is only a general guide to benefits and tax credits and is not a full and authoritative statement of the law.</s> <s>We have made every effort to ensure that the information in this leaflet is correct at the date shown on the cover.</s> <s>However, changes in the law may make the leaflet become gradually less accurate.</s></p>

<p><head><s>Help you may be able to get</s></head></p>

<p><s>Check first what benefits or tax credits you may be able to get.</s></p>

<p><s>If you were working for an employer and earning enough for it to be relevant for National Insurance (NI) purposes (this amount is lower than the amount when you have to start paying NI contributions): check Statutory Sick Pay (SSP) see page 6.</s></p>

<p><s>If you want to know how much you have to earn for it to be relevant for NI purposes, contact your Inland Revenue (NI contributions) office.</s></p>

<p><s>If you were not working when you became sick, you were self-employed or have been sick for more than 28 weeks: check Incapcity Benefit see page 6</s></p>

<p><s>If you are aged 16 or over but under 65, have been unable to work for at least 28 weeks and cannot get Incapacity Benefit: check Severe Disablement Allowance (SDA) see page 7/</s></p>

<p><s>If you are aged under 65 and need help looking after yourself or getting around because of a severe physical or mental disability: check Disability Living Allowance (DLA) see page 8.</s></p>

<p><s>If you are aged 65 or over and need help looking after yourself: check Attendance Allowance (AA) see page 9.</s></p>

<p><s>If you are aged 16 or over, disabled and working 16 hours a week or more: check Disabled Person's Tax Credit see page 10.</s></p>

<p><s>If you are severely disabled as a result of vaccination: check Vaccine damage payments see page 11.</s></p>

<p><s>If you became disabled as a result of an accident at work, or a disease or deafness caused by a job you have done: check Industrial Injuries Disablement Benefit see page 11.</s></p>

<p><s>If you cannot return to your usual work or work with similar pay because of an accident or disease caused by work which occurred before 1 October 1990: check Reduced Earnings Allowance (REA) see page 12.</s></p>e
<p><s>If your illness or disability is caused by work which ended before 5 July 1948, or you are entitled to Workmen's Compensation, you may be able to get benefit.</s> <s>For more information contact:</s> <s>OSD BS(II)</s> <s>Room 7125</s> <s>Norcross</s> <s>Blackpool</s> <s>FY5 3TA</s> <s>Phone 01253 332944</s></p>

<p><s>If you have a disease or were injured at work because of your employer's negligence, you may be able to get compensation through the courts.</s> <s>Ask a solicitor or your trade union.</s></p>

<p><s>If you are caring for someone who is sick or disabled, check if they are getting or waiting to hear about any of these benefits:</s> <s>Disability Living Allowance</s> <s>Attendance Allowance</s> <s>War Pensions Constant Attendance Allowance, or</s> <s>Industrial Injuries Disablement Benefit</s>
<s>Constant Attendance Allowance.</s> <s>If they are, and you are a full-time carer, you may be able to get help: check Invalid Care Allowance (ICA) see page 12.</s></p>

<p><s>You are a full-time carer if you spend at least 35 hours a week looking after someone with a physical or mental illness or disability.</s></p>

<p><s>If you are unable to pay National Insurance (NI) contributions because you are caring for someone: check Home Responsibilities Protection (HRP) see page 14.</s></p>

<p><s>If you and your partner are on a low income and any of the following apply:</s> <s>you are sick or disabled</s> <s>you are aged 60 or over</s> <s>you are a lone parent</s> <s>you are caring for someone who is ill or disabled</s> <s>you are registered or in Scotland certified blind</s> <s>check Income Support see page 15.</s></p>

<p><s>We use partner to mean a person you are married to or a person you are living with as if you are married to them.</s></p>

<p><s>If you were injured or disabled as a result of service in HM Armed Forces or because of a war, you may be able to get help from the War Pension scheme: contact the War Pensions Agency.</s> <s>Write to:</s> <s>The War Pensions Agency</s>
<s>Norcross</s> <s>Blackpool</s> <s>FY5 3WP</s> <s>You can also phone the War Pension Helpline on 0800 169 22 77.</s></p>

<p><head><s>Other help</s></head></p>

<p><s>The Social Fund see page 16.</s></p>

<p><s>Housing Benefit and Council Tax Benefit see page 17.</s></p>

<p><s>Help with health costs see page 17.</s></p>

<p><s>Free milk for disabled children see page 17.</s></p>

<p><head><s>How to claim </s></head></p>

<p><head><s>see page 18.</s></head></p>

<p><head><s>Where to get help and advice</s></head></p>

<p><s>see page 19.</s></p>

<p><head><s>National Insurance (NI)</s></head></p>

<p><s>For some benefits you must have paid or be treated as having paid NI contributions.</s> <s>For more information, contact your social security office.</s></p>

<p><head><s>Statutory Sick Pay (SSP)</s></head></p>

<p><s>Paid by your employer</s> <s>Paid for up to 28 weeks</s></p>

<p><s>Were you:</s> <s>Sick for at least 4 days in a row including weekends and bank holidays?</s> <s>Employed when you became sick?</s> <s>Earning enough on average for it to be relevant for NI purposes (this amount is lower than the amount when you start paying NI contributions)?</s></p>

<p><s>If YES to all, claim SSP.</s></p>

<p><s>If you want to know how much you have to earn for it to be relevant for NI purposes, contact your Inland Revenue office.</s></p>

<p><s>You can get SSP for up to 28 weeks in one spell of sickness.</s> <s>Spells of at least 4 days in a row with 8 weeks or less between them are counted as one spell.</s> <s>If you have more than one job you may be able to claim SSP from each employer.</s></p>

<p><s>If SSP ends, claim Incapacity Benefit.</s></p>

<p><s>How to claim see page 18.</s></p>

<p><head><s>Incapacity Benefit</s></head></p>

<p><s>Paid if SSP has ended or you cannot get SSP</s> <s>Not paid if you were over state pension age when you became sick</s></p>

<p><s>Have you:</s> <s>Paid NI contributions?</s> <s>Been incapable of work because of sickness or disability for at least 4 days in a row including weekends and public holidays?</s></p>

<p><s>If YES to both, claim Incapacity Benefit.</s></p>

<p><s>Short-term Incapacity Benefit at the lower rate</s></p>

<p><s>Paid if you do not get SSP and have been sick for at least 4 days in a row including weekends and Bank Holidays</s></p>

<p><s>Short-term Incapacity Benefit at the higher rate</s></p>

<p><s>Paid if you have been sick for more than 28 weeks and less than 52 weeks.</s></p>

<p><s>Long-term Incapacity Benefit</s></p>

<p><s>Paid if you have been sick for over 52 weeks.</s></p>

<p><s>Special circumstances</s> <s>If you became sick before reaching state pension age, you may be able to get Incapacity Benefit after state pension age.</s> <s>It can be paid at the Retirement Pension rate for up to one year of sickness.</s> <s>If you get the highest rate care component of Disability Living Allowance or you are terminally ill, you will get Incapacity Benefit paid at the long-term rate after you have been sick for 28 weeks.</s> <s>If you get the long-term rate of Incapacity Benefit you may qualify for extra money depending on your age when you became sick.</s> <s>If you have children you may be able to get extra money.</s> <s>This extra money can only be paid with short-term Incapacity Benefit at the higher rate or Retirement Pension rate, or with long-term Incapacity Benefit.</s> <s>If your husband or wife is aged 60 or over, or another adult cares for your children, you may be able to get extra money.</s></p>

<p><s>How to claim see page 18.</s></p>

<p><head><s>Severe Disablement Allowance - SDA</s></head></p>

<p><s>If you have been unable to work for at least 28 weeks in a row because of illness or disability</s> <s>Can be paid if you have never been able to work</s></p>

<p><s>Are you</s> <s>Aged 16 or over and under 65?</s> <s>Unable to get Incapacity Benefit because you have not paid enough NI contributions?</s></p>

<p><s>If YES to both, claim SDA</s></p>

<p><s>If you became unable to work after your 20th birthday your disability will be assessed by a doctor.</s> <s>If you are a student under 19, and your studies are supervised for 21 hours a week or less, you may be able to get SDA.</s> <s>If you have children you may be able to get extra money.</s> <s>If you husband or wife is aged 60 or over, or another adult cares for your children, you may be able to get extra money.</s> <s>If you were entitled to SDA immediately before you became 65, you may be able to carry on getting it.</s></p>

<p><head><s>Disability Living Allowance (DLA)</s></head></p>

<p><s>If you need help looking after yourself</s>
<s>If you claim before your 65th birthday</s>
<s>If you are aged 5 or over and under 65, and have difficulty walking or need help getting around</s>
<s>Paid at different rates</s></p>

<p><s>Have you: Needed help for 3 months because of a severe physical or mental disability, and likely to need it for at least another 6 months?</s></p>

<p><s>If YES, claim DLA.</s></p>

<p><s>There are special rules for people with a terminal illness to help them get benefit for care quickly and easily.</s> <s>If you are getting DLA when you reach age 65, it can continue as long as you still need the help.</s> <s>You can get DLA even if no one is actually giving you the care you need.</s> <s>You may not get DLA if you are in hospital or residential care.</s> <s>DLA is not affected by savings.</s> <s>DLA is not usually affected by other money you have coming in.</s> <s>DLA is usually ignored as income for working out Income Support and Jobseeker's Allowance.</s></p>

<p><s>DLA for children under age 16</s></p>

<p><s>You can claim DLA for a child with a severe physical or mental disability if they need much more help or looking after than other children of the same age because of their illness or disability</s></p>

<p><s>Is the child:</s>
<s>Aged 3 months or over and generally needs extra help or looking after?</s> <s>Aged 5 years or over and needs extra help getting around out of doors?</s></p>

<p><s>If YES to one, claim DLA.</s></p>

<p><s>You can claim DLA before the child is aged 3 months, but DLA will not be paid before the child reaches age 3 months unless they are terminally ill.</s></p>

<p><s>How to claim see page 18.</s></p>

<p><head><s>Attendance Allowance (AA)</s></head></p>

<p><s>If you need help looking after yourself</s>
<s>If you became disabled on or after your 65th birthday, or are claiming on or after your 65th birthday</s>
<s>Paid at different rates depending on whether you need care during the day, during the night, or both</s></p>

<p><s>Have you: Needed help for at least 6 months?</s></p>

<p><s>If YES, claim AA.</s></p>

<p><s>There are special rules for people with a terminal illness to help them get benefit for care quickly and easily.</s> <s>You can get AA even if no one is actually giving you the care you need.</s> <s>You may not get AA if you are in hospital or residential care.</s> <s>AA is not affected by savings.</s> <s>AA is not usually affected by other money you have coming in.</s> <s>AA is usually ignored as income for working out Income Support and Jobseeker's Allowance.</s></p>

<p><s>How to claim see page 18.</s></p>

<p><head><s>Disabled Person's Tax Credit</s></head></p>

<p><s>Savings over £16,000 mean you cannot get Disabled Person's Tax Credit</s></p>

<p><s>Are you:</s>
<s>Aged 16 or over?</s>
<s>Working on average 16 hours a week or more?</s>
<s>Restricted in the type of work, or number of hours, that you can do because of illness or disability?</s></p>

<p><s>Then check the questions below.</s></p>

<p><s>1. Have you:</s>
<s>Been getting one of the following because of your illness or disability, in the last 26 weeks?</s>
<s>Short-term Incapacity Benefit paid at the higher rate</s>
<s>Long-term Incapacity Benefit</s>
<s>Severe Disablement Allowance</s>
<s>Disability premium or higher pensioner premium on: Income Support, income-based Jobseeker's Allowance, Housing Benefit or Council Tax Benefit.</s></p>

<p><s>If YES to any, apply for Disabled Person's Tax Credit</s></p>

<p><s>2. Or are you:</s>
<s>Getting one of the following because of your illness or disability?</s>
<s>Disability Living Allowance</s>
<s>Attendance Allowance</s>
<s>Industrial Injuries Disablement Benefit with Constant Attendance Allowance</s>
<s>War Disablement Pension with War Pensioner's Constant Attendance Allowance  or mobility supplement</s>
<s>An invalid three-wheeler supplied by the DSS</s></p>

<p><s>If YES to any, apply for Disabled Person's Tax Credit.</s></p>

<p><s>Savings over £3,000 affect how much Disabled Person's Tax Credit you can
get.</s>
<s>Voluntary work does not count towards the 16 hours.</s> <s>This could be something like unpaid work for a charity.</s> <s>For more information, get leaflet WK4 Financial help if you work or are doing voluntary work from your social security office.</s>
<s>You can get Disabled Person's Tax Credit if you are employed or self-employed.</s>
<s>You may be able to get help with childcare costs.</s>
<s>You cannot get Disabled Person's Tax Credit if you get an Employment Service or New Deal allowance.</s>
<s>You may get more Disabled Person's Tax Credit if you work 30 hours a week or more.</s>
<s>To find out more about Disabled Person's Tax Credit, phone the information helpline on 0845 605 5858.</s> <s>If you use a textphone, the number is 0845 608 88 44.</s></p>

<p><s>How to apply see page 18.</s></p>

<p><head><s>Vaccine damage payments</s></head></p>

<p><s>A one-off payment if you are severely disabled as a result of vaccination</s>
<s>If you want more information get leaflet HB3 Payment for people severely disabled by a vaccine from your social security office, or write to:</s>
<s>The Vaccine Damage Payments Unit</s>
<s>Palatine House</s>
<s>Lancaster Road</s>
<s>Preston PR1 1HB.</s></p>

<p><head><s>Industrial Injuries Disablement Benefit</s></head></p>

<p><s>You must have done certain types of work</s>
<s>Not paid if you were self-employed when the accident happened or the disease was caused</s>
<s>The amount depends on how serious your disability is</s></p>

<p><s>Are you:</s>
<s>Disabled because of an accident at work?</s>
<s>Disabled by a disease, including deafness, caused by your job?</s></p>

<p><s>If YES to one, claim Industrial Injuries Disablement Benefit.</s></p>

<p><s>If you are claiming because of a disease, you can only get Industrial Injuries Disablement Benefit for listed industrial diseases - check with your social security office.</s>
<s>If you get Industrial Injuries Disablement Benefit, need daily care and attention and your disablement is assessed as 100 per cent, you may get Constant Attendance Allowance (CAA).</s> <s>This is paid at four different rates.</s>
<s>If you get Exceptional or Intermediate rate CAA and you need permanent constant care and attention, you may also get Exceptionally Severe Disablement Allowance.</s></p>

<p><s>How to claim see page 18.</s></p>

<p><head><s>Reduced Earnings Allowance (REA)</s></head></p>

<p><s>Help if you cannot earn as much because of an accident or disease caused by work</s></p>

<p><s>Are you:</s>

<s>Unable to do your usual job or work with similar pay because of an accident or disease?</s>
<s>Suffering from an illness or disability because of an accident or disease which occurred before 1 October 1990?</s></p>

<p><s>If YES to both, claim REA.</s></p>

<p><s>If your REA is £2.00 or more, you reach state pension age and you are not in regular employment, your REA will be replaced by another benefit called Retirement Allowance.</s></p>

<p><s>How to claim see page 18.</s></p>

<p><head><s>Invalid Care Allowance (ICA)</s></head></p>

<p><s>Paid to full-time carers</s>
<s>Your other benefits may increase or decrease</s>
<s>Certain benefits for the person you look after may sometimes reduce.</s></p>

<p><s>Are you:</s>
<s>Aged 16 or over and under 65?</s>
<s>Spending at least 35 hours a week looking after someone who is getting one of these benefits:</s>
<s>- Attendance Allowance?</s>
<s>- Disability Living Allowance at the middle or higher rate for personal care?</s>
<s>- Industrial Injuries Disablement Benefit Constant Attendance Allowance or War Pensions Constant Attendance Allowance?</s></p>

<p><s>If YES to both, claim ICA.</s></p>

<p><s>If the person you care for is getting or waiting to hear about Constant Attendance Allowance under the Industrial Injuries scheme, it must be at the normal maximum rate or above.</s>
<s>If the person you care for is getting or waiting to hear about Constant Attendance Allowance under the War Pensions scheme, it must be at the basic (full day) rate or above.</s>
<s>You cannot get ICA if you are in full-time education.</s>
<s>You must not earn above a certain amount.</s> <s>We will not count money you pay out for things like:</s>
<s>- some National Insurance (NI) contributions</s>
<s>- income tax</s>
<s>- half of any money you pay towards a personal or occupational pension</s>
<s>- paying someone who is not a close relative to look after the disabled person while you are at work (up to a certain limit)</s>
<s>- paying someone who is not a close relative to look after children aged under 16 while you are at work (up to a certain limit)</s>
<s>- some other expenses.</s>
<s>You may be able to get extra money for your family.</s>
<s>ICA may carry on when you become 65 if your Retirement Pension would be less than ICA.</s> <s>You must have been entitled to ICA immediately before your 65th birthday.</s>
<s>You may be able to get extra money added to Income Support, income-based Jobseeker's Allowance, Housing Benefit and Council Tax Benefit.</s> <s>You may be able to get this if you claimed ICA but cannot get it because you already have another benefit paid at a higher amount.</s> <s>Check with your social security office.</s>
<s>If the person you are caring for gets Income Support or income-based Jobseeker's Allowance, they may lose their severe disability premium.</s> <s>Check with their social security office.</s>
<s>If you have a short break from looking after the person you care for, your ICA may be able to continue.</s>
<s>If you want more information about what help is available to carers, get leaflet SD4 Caring for someone? from your social security office.</s></p>

<p><s>How to claim see page 18.</s></p>

<p><head><s>Home Responsibilities Protection (HRP)</s></head></p>

<p><s>HRP is not a benefit, but a scheme you do not have to pay for that helps protect your basic Retirement Pension.</s>
<s>If you are unable to pay NI contributions, or have not paid enough for any year because of caring responsibilities at home, you may be able to get HRP.</s>
<s>If you get Child Benefit in your name for a child under age 16, and you have told us your NI number, you will usually get HRP automatically.</s>
<s>If you spend at least 35 hours a week looking after someone who is claiming Attendance Allowance, Disability Living Allowance at the middle or highest rate for personal care, or Constant Attendance Allowance, you may be able to get HRP.</s>
<s>If you get Income Support because you are caring for someone, you will usually get HRP automatically.</s>
<s>If you get Invalid Care Allowance you will get NI credits and will not usually need HRP.</s>
<s>For a man, HRP can help protect widow's benefits for his wife.</s>
<s>If you are a woman, you cannot get HRP for any year you pay reduced NI contributions for married women and widows.</s>
<s>You can get more information from leaflet CF411 How to protect your state Retirement Pension if you are looking after someone at home.</s> <s>You can get this from your social security office.</s></p>

<p><head><s>Income Support</s></head></p>

<p><s>For people on a low income</s>
<s>Savings over £8,000 usually mean you cannot get Income Support (£16,000 if you live in a residential care or nursing home)</s>
<s>If you have to sign on at the Jobcentre, you cannot get Income Support</s></p>

<p><s>Are you:</s>

<s>Aged 16 or over?</s>
<s>On a low income?</s>
<s>Not working or working on average less than 16 hours a week, and your partner works on average less than 24 hours a week?</s></p>

<p><s>If YES to all, claim Income Support.</s></p>

<p><s>Savings over £3,000 usually affect how much Income Support you can get.</s>
<s>You may be able to get extra money if you are buying your home and you may also get help with some other housing costs.</s>
<s>You can usually get extra money for your family.</s>
<s>If you are sick and not getting SSP you should claim Incapacity Benefit as well as Income Support.</s>
<s>If you get SSP you do not have to claim Incapacity Benefit as well as Income Support.</s>
<s>To see if you can get Income Support because of a low income, check with your social security office.</s>

<p><s>From April 2001, severely disabled people who get the highest rate of Disability Living Allowance for care will usually be able to get more Income Support.</s> <s>This is part of the new Disability Income Guarantee.</s></p>

<p><s>How to claim see page 18.</s></p>

<p><head><s>Other help</s></head></p>

<p><head><s>The Social Fund</s></head></p>

<p><s>Help with exceptional expenses which are hard to pay out of your regular
income.</s>
<s>You may be able to get a Community Care Grant, Budgeting Loan or Crisis Loan to help with things like household items, certain travel costs or in an emergency or disaster.</s>
<s>For Grants you must usually be getting Income Support or income-based Jobseeker's Allowance.</s> <s>For Budgeting Loans you must have been getting one of these benefits for at least 26 weeks.</s> <s>For Crisis Loans you do not have to be getting any benefits.</s>
<s>You do not have to have paid NI contributions to get help from the Social Fund.</s>
<s>Budgeting Loans and Crisis Loans have to be paid back, but they are interest free.</s> <s>Funeral Payments usually have to be paid back from out of the estate of the person who has died.</s> <s>Community Care Grants and other Social Fund payments do not have to be paid back.</s></p>

<p><s>The Social Fund can also help certain people with some other expenses:</s>
<s>Maternity Payments and Sure Start Maternity Grants can help with things a new baby needs immediately.</s>
<s>Funeral Payments can help with the costs of arranging a funeral.</s>
<s>Cold Weather Payments can help with extra heating expenses in cold weather.</s>
<s>Winter Fuel Payments are paid to eligible households that include someone aged 60 or over to help with their winter fuel bills.</s>
<s>You can get more information about Winter Fuel Payments from leaflet WFP1 Important information about Winter Fuel Payments 2000.</s> <s>You can get this from your social security office.</s></p>
<s>If you want any other information on the Social Fund, get leaflet GL18 Help from the Social Fund from your social security office.</s></p>

<p><head><s>Housing Benefit and Council Tax Benefit</s></head></p>

<p><s>Paid by local councils</s>
<s>You do not have to get any other benefits</s></p>

<p><s>Are you:</s>
<s>On a low income?</s>
<s>Paying rent?</s></p>

<p><s>If YES to both, claim Housing Benefit.</s></p>

<p><s>Are you:</s>
<s>On a low income?</s>
<s>Paying council tax?</s></p>

<p><s>If YES to both, claim Council Tax Benefit.</s></p>

<p><s>If you claim Income Support or Jobseeker's Allowance you will get forms to claim Housing Benefit and Council Tax Benefit with your claim pack.</s>
<s>If you do not claim Income Support or Jobseeker's Allowance you can get forms for Housing Benefit and Council Tax Benefit from your local council.</s>
<s>If you want more information get leaflets GL16 Help with your rent and GL17 Help with your council tax.</s> <s>You can get these from your local council offices or your social security office.</s></p>

<p><head><s>Help with health costs</s></head></p>

<p><s>Free NHS prescriptions</s>
<s>Free NHS dental treatment</s>
<s>Free NHS sight tests</s>
<s>Vouchers towards the cost of glasses or contact lenses</s>
<s>Free NHS wigs and fabric supports</s>
<s>Repayment of necessary travel costs to hospital and back for NHS treatment</s></p>

<p><s>Do you or your partner get:</s>
<s>Income Support?</s>
<s>Income-based Jobseeker's Allowance?</s></p>

<p><s>If YES to one, you can get help with health costs.</s></p>

<p><s>If NO, you may be able to get help with health costs through the NHS Low Income Scheme.</s></p>

<p><s>If you want more information get leaflet HC11 Are you entitled to help with health costs?</s>
<s>For information on a range of health-related subjects, phone the Health Information Service on 0800 66 55 44.</s> <s>Calls are confidential</s></p>

<p><head><s>Free milk for disabled children</s></head></p>

<p><s>If you have a child aged 5 or over but under 16 who is unable to attend school because of physical or mental disability</s>
<s>You do not need to get any benefits</s></p>

<p><s>To claim, get form FW20 from:</s>
<s>Disability Benefits Unit</s>
<s>Room C122A</s>
<s>Lobby D</s>
<s>Warbreck House</s>
<s>Warbreck Hill Road</s>
<s>Blackpool</s>
<s>FY2 0YE</s></p>

<p><head><s>How to claim</s></head></p>

<p><head><s>1. When to claim</s></head></p>

<p><s>You must claim Disability Living Allowance before your 65th birthday.</s></p>

<p><s>If you are claiming Industrial Injuries Disablement Benefit because of an accident, claim after you have been disabled because of the accident for two months.</s> <s>For all other benefits in this leaflet, claim straight away.</s> <s>If you delay you may lose benefit.</s></p>

<p><head><s>2. Claim form</s></head></p>

<p><s>Ask your employer about SSP.</s></p>

<p><s>For other benefits, contact your social security office for a claim form.</s> <s>For your nearest social security office, look for the Benefits Agency display advert in the business numbers section of the phone book.</s></p>

<p><s>To apply for Disabled Person's Tax Credit, get an application pack from
Inland Revenue enquiry centres, your social security office or Jobcentre.</s> <s>For your nearest Inland Revenue enquiry centre, look for Inland Revenue in the business numbers section of the phone book.</s></p>

<p><head><s>3. Filling in the form</s></head></p>

<p><s>Before you fill in your form, check that you are applying for everything you may be entitled to.</s> <s>Use this leaflet as a guide.</s></p>

<p><head><s>4. Proof of identity</s></head></p>

<p><s>It is important that we can be sure of your identity when you make a claim.</s> <s>We may need to ask you about your background and look at any official documents you have to support the information you give.</s></p>

<p><s>If you are not sure about this, get leaflet GL25 How to prove your identity for social security from your social security office.</s></p>

<p><head><s>Where to get help and advice</s></head></p>

<p><s>To get more information or other leaflets get in touch with your social security office.</s> <s>For your nearest social security office, look for the Benefits Agency display advert in the business numbers section of the phone book.</s></p>

<p><s>You can get more information from the DSS website.</s> <s>The address is:
http://www.dss.gov.uk</s></p>

<p><s>The email address is: baadmin@baadmin.demon.co.uk</s></p>

<p><s>A confidential telephone service is available for people with disabilities and their carers.</s> <s>Ring the Benefit Enquiry Line (BEL) on 0800 88 22 00.</s> <s>People with speech or hearing problems using a textphone can dial 0800 24 33 55.</s></p>

<p><s>The person taking your call will not have your personal papers but will be able to give you general advice.</s> <s>This advice must not be taken as a decision on any matter about which you are making an enquiry.</s></p>

<p><s>There are other benefits which you may be able to get.</s> <s>You can get information on them from other leaflets:</s></p>

<p><s>BC1 Babies and children</s> <s>A guide to benefits and tax credits for anyone expecting a baby or caring for children</s></p>

<p><s>RM1 Retirement</s> <s>A guide to benefits for people who are retiring or have retired</s></p>

<p><s>GL21 A helping hand for benefits?</s> <s>How somebody with an illness or disability can get help to collect or deal with social security benefits</s></p>

<p><s>GL12 Going into hospital?</s></p>

<p><s>GL23 Social security benefit rates</s></p>

<p><s>HB6 A practical guide for disabled people</s> <s>A guide to services other than benefits for people with disabilities.</s> <s>You can get this by writing to:</s>
<s>Department of Health</s>
<s>PO Box 777</s>
<s>London</s>
<s>SE1 6HX.</s></p>

<p><head><s>Other formats</s></head></p>

<p><s>This leaflet is also available in large print, braille, on audio cassette and in the following languages:</s>
<s>Arabic</s> <s>Bengali</s> <s>Chinese</s> <s>Gujarati</s> <s>Punjabi</s> <s>Somali</s> <s>Urdu</s> <s>Vietnamese.</s></p>

<p><s>You can get these from your social security office.</s></p>

<p><s>Leaflet SD1 from October 2000.</s> <s>Replaces leaflet SD1 April 2000.</s> <s>Produced by DSS Communications (Leeds).</s></p>

</body>
</text>
</cesDoc>
